Boker tov, we are on the last דף Daf of בבא מציעא
Bava Metzia today, קי"ט. Kuf Yud Tet. A short דף, Daf, we're
a little bit behind, but I have no fear we will catch
up today.
So we pick up on, see how well you guys can make
take can help or her or prevent that from happening. We pick
up on קי"ח עמוד ב'. Kuf Yud Chet Amud Bet. We're in
the middle of, we now sort of shifted from a פרק Perek
that deals with
ground floor and a top floor and whose responsibility it is when
things break or when the floor breaks through and so on to
issues of neighbors
and your wall or your tree falling into your neighbor's yard and
then we had questions about rights of use of רשות הרבים Reshus
Harabim for certain types of, as somebody said at the end of
yesterday, it's not like רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim was completely sort of
neutral territory that everybody shares one use, like as a way of
going as a street. I mean there are different רשות הרבים. Reshus
Harabim. There was those that were thoroughfares and there's those that were
more like plazas, but actually is almost like people have rights to
do their individual things there, you can be making your plaster in
רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, and you can
be taking delivery of the fertilizer and delivering it to somebody else.
But obviously with all of that it has to be in a
way in which respects and doesn't compromise the right of the רבים
Rabim to use it for other things and doesn't create potential hazards
and so on. And there really are two issues and this is
going to be a continuing theme in בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, right,
about we discussed also like you operating in your own domain but
it causes somebody else damage, like plant my tree but then the
roots go and they destroy your well. So there are two questions
about that. What is the degree of freedom I have in my
own domain? Do I have to act in ways that prevent indirect
damage to you or not? Or do I have absolute freedom and
it's your responsibility, על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו או על הניזק להרחיק
את עצמו. Al Hamazik Leharchik Et Atzmo O Al Hanizak Leharchik Et
Atzmo. And then there's a second degree question which is if you
actually do get damaged as a result, am I חייב Chayav or
not, which is like a בבא קמא Bava Kamma type of a
question. And the same issue is about רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. Do
I have a right to do certain things in רשות הרבים? Reshus
Harabim? Can I go ahead and empty my refuse in רשות הרבים
Reshus Harabim or not? Or am I not allowed to do that
because it might create a hazard? And even if I do have
a right to do it, maybe I would still be liable if
somebody got injured. You could go both ways. You could say if
somebody got injured, I wouldn't be liable because it's indirect or whatever.
But nevertheless, I can't do it because I create a hazard. That
I think makes the most sense to think that even in cases
where you might not be liable, you're not allowed to do it
because you're creating a hazard. Or it could be the reverse. It
could be that I am allowed to do it, but I have
to assume the risk of paying if somebody gets damaged as a
result and we saw that as well, פותחין בביבר ברשות הרבים. Potchin
Bevibar Birshus Harabim.
And even though you have a right to do certain things, you
might be liable. So that issue of operating within your own private
domain or operating within the public domain, what's the degree of freedom
and rights that you have to do things and how much do
you have to be concerned about the neighbors or the public's welfare?
And then the question about liability after the fact, that's the issues
that we've been dealing with and those are very much issues that
are going to continue on through the beginning of בבא בתרא. Bava
Basra. So as again as I said, this last פרק Perek really
should have been the first פרק Perek of בבא בתרא. Bava Basra.
But be that as it may. Okay, so now we pick up
in the middle of קי"ח עמוד ב' Kuf Yud Chet Amud Bet
the following.
Let's pick up with this.
אמר אביי רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון גמליאל. Amar Abaye Rabbi Yehuda VeRabbi
Shimon Gamliel. The line starts with the word רבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel. It is
eight lines down from the wide lines. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, רבי
יהודה ורבי שמעון גמליאל ורבי שמעון, Rabbi Yehuda VeRabbi Shimon Gamliel VeRabbi
Shimon, those three תנאים, Tannaim, כולהו סבירא להו. Kulhu Sevira Lehu. They
all hold, אביי Abaye is a big one to collect different opinions
of תנאים Tannaim and to try to claim that they're coming from
more or less a similar position. So they all hold this following
position. כולהו סבירא להו כל מקום שנתנו לו חכמים רשות והזיק פטור.
Kulhu Sevira Lehu Kol Makom Shenatnu Lo Chachamim Reshus Vehizik Patur.
That if you do have the permission to act in this way,
you will not be liable if somebody gets damaged as a result.
So exactly that question of those two way two possible considerations, do
you have the right to do it and are you liable? אביי
Abaye says that these group of חכמים Chachamim hold a very reasonable
position that if we're permitting you to do this activity, it comes
with freeing you, waiving any possible liability as a result.
Before, not everybody holds that, but these three תנאים Tannaim do.
רבי יהודה הא דאמרן, Rabbi Yehuda Had De-amran, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
the one we just said because we quoted a ברייתא Brayta earlier
about רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda on חנוכה Chanukah and other רבי יהודות
Rabbi Yehudas that says if you're operating ברשות, Birshus, you're going to
be
פטור. Patur. רבי שמעון גמליאל דתנן, Rabbi Shimon Gamliel Detnan, רבי שמעון
גמליאל Rabbi Shimon Gamliel because we have the following משנה. Mishnah. רבי
שמעון
גמליאל
אומר אף מתקן הוא את מלאכתו לפני שלשים יום. Rabbi Shimon Gamliel
Omer Af Metaken Hu Et Melachto Lifnei Shloshim Yom. Right, this was
in our משנה Mishnah as well that he says that the משנה
Mishnah said that
if you're building... if you're doing a construction in רשות הרבים *Reshus
Harabim*, you've been hired to build a wall in רשות הרבים *Reshus
Harabim*. So it says basically you know you have to like take
delivery and build right away, you can't leave all your building material
in the middle of the street, okay? And then it says but
if somebody gets damaged as a result, even though you have been
authorized and licensed to build in רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim*, you would
be חייב chayav. *chayav*. And רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says, you know
what? You can even the month leading up to the building, you
can even go ahead and get your sort of, you know, get
the site ready and get all the materials there and so on.
Now, רש"י *Rashi* doesn't say explicitly that you would be פטור patur,
*patur*, but somehow the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* reads in רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel*, the fact that he's giving you such a latitude to prepare
things a month in advance, presumably means that you would be פטור
*patur* if something happened. Okay, so that, and רש"י *Rashi* says maybe
it's through the word אף מתקן metaken, הוא את מלאכתו *af metaken
hu es melachto*. You're saying you'd be חייב chayav *chayav* if somebody
gets damaged? I'm saying somebody can even prepare his work for a
month before. So like, you know, it's almost like a,
like, you know, like sort of a shocking reaction to the position
that you'd be חייב chayav. *chayav*. So that's how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* reads it, okay, that you would be פטור *patur* if something
happened. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, דתנן *detnan*, now how about
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*? Because we talk, היה מעמידו *haya
maamido*, this is again, this is a משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* in בבא
בתרא Bava Basra. *Bava Batra*. היה מעמידו בעלייה *haya maamido ba'aliya*, צריך
שיהא תחתיו מעזיבה שלשה טפחים *tzarich she'yehei tachtav maaziva shlosha tfachim*. So
we have another בית *bayis* and an עלייה *aliya* case, one person
is in the ground floor, one person's on the top floor. And
I want to put my nice wood-burning תנור *tanur* or, you know,
on one of the floors. There's only a little problem, I gotta
make sure you know it satisfies the fire code, it's not a
fire hazard. All right, and it's one thing, you know, obviously, you
know, it's not just enough for me to put my own house
on fire, but it's also your house, you're either on the top
floor or the bottom floor. Okay, so if you're putting the stove
on the top floor, היה מעמידו בעלייה צריך שיהא תחתיו מעזיבה שלשה
טפחים *haya maamido ba'aliya tzarich she'yehei tachtav maaziva shlosha tfachim*. It has
to be underneath it, it has to be plaster שלשה טפחים *shlosha
tfachim* thick so the heat doesn't break through the plaster. If you're
on the bottom floor it also speaks about how high, you know,
the ceiling has to be above the top of the תנור *tanur*.
Okay, and if it's on the top floor it's how thick the
floor has to be. ובכירה *u'bekira*, now that's a תנור *tanur*, כירה
*kira* is less hot, so טפח *tefach*. It only has to be
a טפח *tefach* of plaster. Now let's say ואם הזיק משלם מה
שהזיק *v'im hiziq m'shalem mah she-hiziq*. And even if you've taken care
of making everything according to code, if it actually led to a
fire and it burnt down and you damaged the other person's part
of the building, you have to pay. So although you have a
license to do it, it does not exempt you from payment. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר לא אמרו כל השיעורים הללו אלא שאם הזיק
פטור מלשלם *Rabbi Shimon omer lo amru kol hashiurim elah she'im hiziq
patur mi-leshalem*. No, the point of these things was only to tell
you that you would be פטור *patur*. Now, it's a question if
he literally mean it was only to tell you that you would
be פטור *patur*. Do you have no responsibility to act this way
if you're willing to pay? Let's say you say to the בית
דין *Beis Din*, listen, I will put the whole value of the
house, the value of the guy on the bottom floor, his value
of his house is a million dollars. I'm going to put a
million dollars in escrow and I'm going to go ahead and put
my, you know, and build and put my תנור *tanur* there without
any, without doing it to code. Is he, does he literally mean
the only reason that we're that you have to do it to
code is to ensure the guy will get paid in the end,
or is he just, is that a little bit of a rhetorical
expression? He means, look, obviously you have a responsibility, you know, to
prevent you know things from happening even if you're willing to pay.
But once you've acted accordingly, once you have acted in a way
that's according to the parameters we set, that is going to exempt
you from payment. Okay, so I don't, I wouldn't read it as
literally as the whole purpose for this is because the only thing
we care about is whether the guy will get paid at the
end. I believe everybody agrees we also care about acting in a
way that's not going to cause damage, regardless of if you're willing
to pay. But what he's saying is, once you've acted according to
the parameters and you're doing something we say this will be allowed
when you do it according to these parameters, acting that way in
your own domain certainly frees you then from having to pay if
something goes wrong. So this is going to be a very important
question as we get to בבא בתרא Bava Basra. *Bava Batra*, these
two different levels of consideration: how am I, what's my freedom to
act because I might damage other people even when I'm acting in
my own domain, and what is the consequence if somebody does get
damaged, and those don't necessarily follow one from another, but אביי *Abaye*
says for these three תנאים *Tannaim* it does. If you have the
freedom to act, you are going to be פטור *patur* from payment.
Yes, I understand. I could say for instance I bring my שור
*shor* into your yard. Yeah. You give me permission and then my
שור *shor* bites your שור *shor*.
Right. No, there's whole discussions in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about that,
that once I tell you you can come in that I might
exempt you whatever, but anyway, but
these guys would hold on that side of it?
No, but that's a different point because there you're not operating in
your own domain.
It's simply because it's his own domain.
Yeah, these are things or רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim*. I mean רשות
הרבים *Reshus Harabim* is maybe a little bit more parallel to your
case, right, but there I think that there's a question about, doesn't
mean every time... I don't understand, you know, I mean some people
say by the way going back to בבא קמא Bava Kamma *Bava
Kamma* that the reason a שור *shor*, the reason שן ורגל *shen
v'regel* is פטור *patur* in רשות הרבים *Reshus Harabim* is because since
I have a right to have my animal go in רשות הרבים
*Reshus Harabim* and this is a natural type of a thing that
might happen, you can't give me the right to do it and
at the same time make me liable, because that's effectively telling me
I don't have a right, you know, because then I won't be
able to. to do it or whatever. So if you want to
give me that freedom, you have to free me from the consequence.
So it is an ongoing question and you're right, you need to
look at different scenarios, but certainly all of the cases now with
these cases bridged the case of private and public, like the last
two—the last one was operating in your private domain with that type
of a permission, and the first two are operating in the public
domain with that permission. Okay, and some of that comes with that
sense of freeing from liability, yes.
It's a קשיא in other words, right? In other words, in one
is שלשים יום shloshim yom you can even be מתקן, פטור, yeah.
But here, you've built your furnace by code, but if it does
damage you still have to pay.
Yeah, but that's a תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon.
says you're exempt. ולא אמרו כל השיעורים הללו אלא שאם הזיק פטור
מלשלם.
v’lo amru kol hashiurim
halalu
ela she-im hizik patur milishalem. Okay, so that little section of גמרא
Gemara is like the core issues of everything going on in the
beginning of בבא בתרא. All right, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Now we're
going to deal with if you are liable, like the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, that even though you have permission, something goes wrong, you
could be liable. I have to tell you, I don't fully understand
some of the issues about what we're going to read. Let's take
a look. It seems very simple.
החצב שמסר לסתת, hachatzav shemasar lesatat, if the guy who's
banging the hewing I guess is the word the stone out of
the mountain, he hands the stone over to the מסתת, mesatet, to
the guy who does
the cutter, right, or the guy who smoothes it or whatever, there's
a word like planes it. You plane wood, right? Is that what
it's called, planing? What?
Planing's from wood.
Yeah. לסתת lesatat is the hewing, החצב hachatzav is like a quarry,
no, you get the stone out of the mountain?
I thought that's to hew is to get the stone out of
the mountain.
Okay, we get the word quarrying. Okay.
Anyway, the חצב chatzav is the guy who removes the stone from
the mountain. The סתת satat is the guy who then like smoothes
it up and shapes it into the right size. Okay. Although I
do have to tell you again, I mentioned the tunnel tours yesterday
that actually at the end of the tunnel tours it's fascinating because
at the very end of the tunnel you see like they were
sort of like at the end of the Western Wall essentially that
where what it was at before like right when it was destroyed,
and they first of all they've got on the floor are these
perfect square tiles, like big square tiles, and from the Roman period.
And there's one standing up pristine that they never got around to
laying, like a pristine square tile that they have never laid, and
then you go a little bit just like two feet further and
you start to see this because this was the quarry, they were
quarrying the stones for the wall from the edge there, and you
see there's like this section here in the ground and there's this
section of stones that are sort of like this, sort of into
the
ground. And you sort of see that they're starting to—they're like carving
it in the ground and they're going to carve that stone and
then they don't remove like a big boulder and then smooth it,
they sort of cut it into the stone and then they take
it out. Anyway. All right.
So where are we? So the guy who takes it out of
the mountain, I think it's the hewer, gives it to the guy
who does the sort of the planing or whatever it's called, the
cutting and to make it into the right size and the smoothing.
הסתת חייב. hasatat chayav.
And then the guy who is smoothing it, it slipped out of
his hand and it broke something, so he's חייב. chayav. Okay, because
presumably here we're dealing with an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. Okay, it
was your stone, I mean I don't care if you own the
stone or not. I say Michael, hold onto my knife. And Michael
holds onto my knife and it slips out of his hand and
it hurts somebody, it falls on somebody's foot. He's חייב chayav. as
an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. It doesn't matter who owns the knife.
Okay? הסתת חייב. hasatat chayav. סתת שמסר לחמר. satat shemasar lechamar. Now
the guy finished cutting it into the right shape and he gave
it to the donkey driver, to the conveyor, to the guy the
truck driver. החמר חייב. hachamar chayav. And then it presumably fell off
the guy's donkey or something and then he's חייב. chayav. Okay. חמר
שמסר לכתף. chamar shemasar lekatef. And then the truck driver gave it
to the worker at the worksite to bring it that's like the
porter. הכתף חייב. hakatef chayav. He's חייב. Chayav כתף שמסר לבנאי. katef
shemasar lebanai. Now the worker who the porter gave it to the
guy who's actually doing the construction himself and then it fell from
the guy who's doing the construction or something. הבנאי חייב. habanai chayav.
The builder's חייב. Chayav. בנאי שמסר לאדריכל. banai shemasar leadrichal. Okay, so
then the worker handed it over to the foreman. אדריכל חייב. adrichal
chayav. The foreman is חייב. Chayav I love this, it is so
concrete, it's so much like you said to see the actual image
of a worksite.
It makes me see in אבות, Avos, it's like the opposite, like
that's all abstract.
Right,
exactly. Okay. אדריכל חייב. adrichal chayav.
Does the foreman actually touch it or is he like?
I guess, I don't know. So that's a good question. I understand
and that's what I'm going to get to the last line. At
a certain point if it falls from me I'm an אדם המזיק,
adam hamazik, but let's say I don't pick it up and it
falls from me. Let's say it's under my Michael is asking the
right question. You, you're the worker, you came, you put it in
front of me, I say, okay put it down here, we'll get
to that later today. And then, you know, I haven't touched it,
but something happened and it slipped down a mountain and it hurt
somebody. So that's, you know, or let's say when it speaks about
what do you call it? The, you know, the חמר, Chamar, the
donkey driver, if it falls off of my wagon, okay that's not
אדם המזיק. Adam Hamazik. What is that? Is that אש? Esh? Is
that, you know, we could start doing a whole בבא קמא Bava
Kamma discussion. But who owns it? Does it matter who owns it?
Like this gets into the early בבא קמא Bava Kamma issues about,
you know, like a type of a שומר Shomer if you're responsible
for it even if you don't own it, does it become like
your property, then you're חייב Chayav for damage that ensues which is
what it sounds like. But that's what I said on the surface
it seems very simple, but it is an important question about what
category do you put this in? Like whose stone is this anyway?
You know, it might belong to the ציבור. Tzibur. They might have
hired me to do the whole construction thing, so it's I don't
have property rights in it. Let's keep on reading cause the last
is the most interesting. והניח אבן על הדימוס, Vehiniach even al hadimus,
if
once they put the stone actually on the what's it called on
the actual like mold? Yeah, the frame, the דימוס Dimus like the
I mean the דימוס Dimus is the actual like you put it
onto the building itself. There's a word for that. How they translate?
Do we have a translation for דימוס? Dimus?
It's a place on the
top row of stones.
Top row of stones. Okay, right. So you put it on the
actual building itself on the stones themselves והזיקה Vehizika and then it
does damage, so presumably it falls off the wall collapses. כולן חייבין
לשלם, Kulan chayavin leshalem,
everybody has to pay.
Even the guy who hewed it out
of the mountain has to pay? Right, so first of all, yeah,
exactly. So what's going on here? Like the guy who hewed it
out of the mountain? Like who did the negligence? Was somebody negligent
when they put it on the top? So then let the negligent
guy pay. Okay, or was it just nobody was negligent? We all
did a good job and then, you know, and then it just
collapsed. Things happen. Okay so then you could ask in general if
just nobody was negligent it's אונס, Ones, you know, whatever the ארבע
אבות נזיקין Arba Avot Nezikin are whatever it is. So you know
the assumption here is somehow that you hired, you all are my
are my crew, okay? We've all been hired to build this building.
We all work for one company. Okay we've all have our different
tasks. You hew it out of the mountain, you carve it, you're
the donkey driver, okay but we're all also like one corporate entity,
it seems to be. It's not like different people have been hired
to do different jobs that wouldn't make any sense. And as one
sort of corporate entity we all take shared responsibility
like you know I guess not at every stage cause at individual
stages it's your own responsibility, but in terms of the final job
we take shared responsibility. Now if you thought about this in context
of a corporation it makes sense, right? You know, if I went
ahead and I build something and as a result people got injured
or whatever, you know, then certainly if you can find negligence you
sue the corporation you don't sue the individual who you know necessarily
who made the particular decision. You look at us as a type
of you know or did the particular act. You look at us
as having shared and corporate responsibility. But I don't know to me
this is a big חידוש. Chiddush. We're not halachically שותפים. Shutafim. הלכה
Halacha normally doesn't know of an idea of corporation. You know who
has who is negligent? Which of the ארבע אבות נזיקין Arba Avot
Nezikin is this? So there's like a lot of questions I think
that aren't answered. But let me just finish reading it, okay. והתניא
Vehatanya don't we teach in a ברייתא Braita אחרון חייב וכולן פטורים?
Acharon chayav vekulan pturim?
It's only the last guy who's חייב. Chayav. Okay cause that at
least makes most sense. It's sort of like the well you know
people different people watching a well and the last guy who was
watching it becomes חייב chayiv? if you remember that case. So לא
קשיא Lo kashya כאן בשכירות כאן בקבלנות Kan biskirut kan bekablanut and
this is it points us to if you're
being hired for the individual job if you're hired labor so then
you know each person is a separate person. I'm hiring you to
do this and you to do that and you to do that
so the last person is חייב chayiv, is you know has the
responsibility. If it's קבלנות Kablanut
we conceptualize it for the whole job. I'm hiring all of you
to get the whole job done. I'm not hiring you for individual
hours or individual tasks I'm hiring you for the whole job. And
because I'm hiring the whole group of you for the whole job
it's more of this corporate responsibility. Only in the last stage? Yeah
and until then I know right and until then it is the
individual responsibility as long as there's an individual to if it comes
directly from an individual. So to me this is all a huge
חידוש Chiddush and I haven't really fully parsed this. Rabbi Dofers had
a question then Gloria.
Yeah you know what I would have liked better first of all
it seems like they do have the like a proto-corporate I know
that's what I'm pointing out yeah. I would
have liked it better if let's say it fell off the חמר.
Chamar. Yeah then the חמר Chamar and the סתת Satat and the
חוצב Chotzev
should have been linked
up everyone until then that was curious. Right. Why is it corporate
only at the very end?
Well only at the because at the end nobody is directly involved.
We put it up on the building and we all walk went
home. As long as one person is directly responsible if at any
time you can say who's responsible for this stone right now? Oh
you cause you were the last guy whatever. Yo you're the foreman
you're the guy carrying it so if we can point out the
guy responsible he's חייב. chayav But after you put it up who's
responsible? None none of us or all of us are responsible.
Like when the windows flew out of the John Hancock building in
Boston you know. No, okay. I know. Right. They built the building,
and then the windows, the thick glass flew out onto the streets
of downtown Boston. Okay. So like the whole corporation. Right.
But I mean look at Rashi. Read the last Rashi. בקבלנות bekablanus
כולן חייבין kulan chayavin היכא דלא נפלו heicha delo naflu מיד אחד
מהן miyad echad mehen דעל כולן de'al kulan לשמור lishmor שתהא יושבת
יפה. she'tehei yoshevet yafe.
Now Rashi does say they all have a joint responsibility. Now Rashi
says לא נפלו מיד אחד מהן. lo naflu miyad echad mehen. Let's
say, because this is a question I raised, let's say at an
earlier stage it fell off of my wagon, but it didn't fall
from my hand, it just fell off my— what does he literally
mean מיד? miyad? If you can't make it אדם המזיק, adam hamazik,
we're equally חייב? chayav Or does he just mean when it didn't,
when it wasn't one particular person's responsibility? You had a question Michael?
My first person—
I'm sorry, right Gloria, I apologize.
I was just thinking that this sounds more like in US law
today there are things that have strict liability where we don't look
to see if there's any fault, but there are certain things where
we decide it's inherently dangerous
and
whatever happens for whatever reason we assign... That's interesting.
So you're saying maybe to look at this as an exception to
the sort of בבא קמא Bava Kamma. rules? To say you're doing
a building construction in the public, meaning if this was somebody building
people in my yard and something fell off into your yard, it
might be a different consideration, but a building sort of construction in
the public thoroughfare is a potential big hazard to the public, maybe
we have to change some of the rules about this. That's an
interesting thought, like to see this as a as a special case.
And you know just in the way like, you know that if
it's my house let's say, then when I move into it, obviously
at some point I'm חייב, chayav but you know it's when someone's
building...
Right, but that's because right that's because then you become the owner.
But Gloria's not saying the absence of an owner, she's saying the
presence of a public hazard.
But again, let's say you build it on my yard, but then
you know at some point like the ownership changes later, it's your
fault because you built it wrong. Right, clearly. I mean that's also
a good question too, just in the public aspect. Let's right, you're
right, I mean let's say we build it, we give it over
to the public, the public's been using this for the last 10
years, and then, or whatever, a year, something, and then something happens,
you know, which clearly was based on some earlier construction aspect. So
maybe yes, maybe because it's public and not a private individual, the
public can still go back to the company. I don't know. Like,
it's really interesting, you know, because this is not the type of
of calculus we're used to from בבא קמא. So it's really interesting.
Yeah, it just seems to me that you can't accept anything without
having it to check, like in building. Like a building code here,
in California you know, at every step you have to make sure
that whatever was done until now is fine, because once I take
this stone from
whoever had it, then now it's on me. Like until... Right. So
you're right, you're saying having this rule creates a very high level
of care, which makes sense again in terms of the public's care,
the public welfare. Okay, excellent. Okay,
let's go to the next משנה. Mishnah See, I was afraid we
wouldn't have enough to say today. שתי גנות, shtei ginos, okay, זו
אגב זו. zo agav zo.
So now we've got our two gardens, vegetable gardens, okay,
and here, this is Reuven's yard, and here's his vegetables growing, okay,
here here he's got his carrots. Okay,
and here is Shimon's yard, okay, and we're gonna have some potatoes.
Okay, whatever. Okay, anyway, there are their yards. שתי גנות זו אגב
זו. shtei ginos zo agav zo. והירק בינתיים. v'hayerak baintayim. And here
you've got some vegetable growing here.
Now,
the question is, well, presumably now, as let's— I you know, the
you might want to say who planted it, but I don't know,
let's say it fell from an errant seed. You don't know who
planted it.
No, but the guy's carrots...
well fine, it doesn't matter. We'll have them all have carrots. Okay,
fine. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara never actually asks who planted it, presumably
it grew wild or something of that nature, okay, and the question
is, who has rights to it? It's under my ground, but it's
in your airspace. Okay. So, והירק בינתיים. v'hayerak baintayim. רבי מאיר אומר
של עליון, Rabbi Meir omer shel elyon, it's Reuven's, it's growing from
his ground. רבי יהודה אומר של תחתון, Rabbi Yehuda omer shel tachton,
it's
Shimon's, it's growing in his airspace. אמר רבי מאיר אם ירצה עליון
ליקח את עפרו אין כאן ירק.
Amar Rabbi Meir im yirtzeh elyon likach et
afaro ein kan yarak.
Reuven could just take his dirt, he could just dig away all
of this dirt and then, I'm sorry, and then there won't be
a vegetable. He has rights to all this dirt, so that proves
that it's his dirt, and therefore proves that it's his vegetable. Correct.
Okay, let's keep on going. אם ירצה ליקח את עפרו... im yirtzeh
likach et afaro... אמר רבי יהודה אם ירצה תחתון למלאות את גנתו
אין כאן ירק. Amar Rabbi Yehuda im yirtzeh tachton l'malot et ginato
ein kan yarak.
If Shimon wants to go ahead and fill this up with dirt,
it'll also destroy the vegetable, okay? So it's just way of proving,
it's another way of saying it's one guy's airspace, it's the other
guy's dirt. So what are you gonna do? And they both ultimately
control the fate of the vegetable. Okay. So, אמר רבי מאיר, Amar
Rabbi Meir, says Rabbi Meir, מאחר ששניהם יכולין למחות, me'achar she'shneihem yacholin
limchos, since each one can... prevent the vegetable from growing, has control
here, זה על זה, zeh al zeh, רואים מהיכן ירק זה חי.
ro'im meiheichan yerek zeh chai.
So you say fine, so therefore, they both have certain rights. So
what should be should should win out is go where it's growing
from, right? And it's growing from the dirt of one. Now, of
course, one does wonder if it's a difference between a vegetable and
a tree. Because vegetable, now not all, do all vegetables grow underground?
No. No. Cucumbers, whatever, what? Tomatoes are technically fruit, but in the
גמרא Gemara. they're probably vegetables, right? Lettuce. Right. Right.
So it is interesting, right? I mean this maybe is deceptive, because
if it's growing above ground, you more hear, you know, I'm sorry
that's me, I'm borrowing my son's, how do you stop this? I'm
borrowing my son's thing here.
It's okay Rabbi, it's okay.
Now you know, now you know the music my son listens to.
Let's figure that out. Okay.
All right. Good thing it wasn't something else. I don't know. All
right. Anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, and if you tell
him to take us, so anyway, yeah. So if it's if it
actually is something that grows above ground, you know, you almost then
then it's a lot more unclear who should be right. It's one
thing that, okay, it grows from the ground, it pulls up the
nutrients from the ground, thank you, it also needs the oxygen, and
it also is actually present in one in in the other person's
airspace if it grows above ground. Right? So I did it this
way, it's very deceptive because you would really think Reuven's, but if
it's growing above ground. Doesn't it say airspace? Why would it matter?
Air. He means the ground.
Everything is rooted
in the ground
so the lettuce happens to be on top and the cabbage. Yeah,
but if you would say, but
if you've got something growing above ground, and you'd say whose is
it, okay, I just think the fact that physically it's present in
Shimon's airspace, even though it's growing from Reuven's dirt, you know, makes
it Reuven's? No, they're under the ground, they're totally Reuven's. No, but
the stuff you care about is under the ground. Anyway, the משנה's
mishna not distinguishing.
Reuven's ground goes all the way.
Yes. Yes. All of this is Reuven's ground. Reuven owns all of
this all of this ground. Okay. Look at this angle. I mean,
if you want, you don't even have to view it as an
angle, okay, if that makes it easier for you to think. Okay.
Does that make it easier? Okay, fine. All of that is Reuven's
ground. Anyway, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, if its roots are
in the ground, if it's the ground if its roots are in
it goes from where the roots are, from where it's getting the
nutrients. Okay. אמר רבי מאיר מאחר ששניהם יכולים למחות זה על זה
רואים מהיכן ירק זה חי. Amar Rabbi Meir me'achar sheshneihem yecholim limchot
zeh al zeh ro'im meiheichan yerek zeh chai. Okay, so that's רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir just reiterating his position. Okay. אמר רבי שמעון כל
שהעליון יכול לפשוט את ידו וליטול הרי זה שלו והשאר של תחתון.
Amar Rabbi Shimon kol sheha'elyon yachol lifshot et yado velitol harei zeh
shelo vehashear shel tachton. רבי Rabbi... שמעון Shimon has a different way
of compromising, or not compromising, until now it's one or the other.
אמר רבי שמעון כל שהעליון יכול לפשוט את ידו וליטול הרי זה
שלו והשאר של תחתון. Amar Rabbi Shimon kol sheha'elyon yachol lifshot et
yado velitol harei zeh shelo vehashear shel tachton. It goes by physical
access. If you're standing here and you lean over and pull it
out, okay, now the question is let's say you can touch the
top but not the roots or whatever, the גמרא Gemara will discuss
some of that, but if you have physical access, it's yours. Otherwise,
it's the guy at the bottom. Because you guess that, you know,
something is high but on my wall I have more access, I
just stand on a ladder or something, than a guy who's up
there. Reuven can't reach it though. Correct. As long as Reuven can't
reach it, it's Shimon's. So he completely goes by the question of
like physical of location and access. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא. Rava. What? I thought
that he can't reach it. Because it's a very steep, short arm,
it's growing. It's very steep, right? Imagine that this is twenty feet
high and imagine that this is growing over here. Right? How is
he supposed to go ahead and reach it? Somebody's going to lower
him down by a rope? You know what I'm saying? He can't
physically lean over. He could dig down. Yeah, what? He could dig
down, but that's not the last position is not
imagining theoretically. It's saying right now the way the setup is, do
you have physical access to it or
not? Okay. All right. אמר רבא בעיקרו כולי עלמא לא פליגי דעליון
הוי כי פליגי בנופו. Amar Rava be'ikaro kulei alma lo pligi de'elyon
havei ki pligi benofo. Okay, now, now רבא Rava actually so makes
this distinction about does it matter what's above ground or what's below
ground? רבא Rava says stuff that's growing below the ground, עיקרו, ikaro,
everybody agrees belongs to Reuven. So if it's carrots, Reuven totally wins
out. Fine, you keep the green of the carrot, what do I
care? Okay? The stuff that's growing below the ground, it's physically in
my location and growing from my stuff, everybody agrees that's Reuven's. So
therefore, that's not the interesting case. The interesting case is that we're
talking about let's say, you know, tomatoes that are here growing on
a vine and their roots are here. So the question is the
stuff that the stuff that's above ground is the stuff that we
want. So on the one hand it's in your airspace. And on
the other hand, it's growing from my ground. That's a more interesting
case. עיקרו כולי עלמא לא פליגי דדיליה. ikaro kuley alma lo pligi
d'dileh.
Regarding the stuff below ground, everybody agrees that's ראובן's. Reuven הא כי
פליגי בנופא. Ha ki pligi b'nofa. We argue about the stuff that
literally is like the foliage, meaning the stuff that's growing from the
roots that's in the air. רבי מאיר סבר שדי נוף בתר עיקר,
Rabbi Meir savar shadi nof batar ikar, the stuff that is, this
is a phrase that the גמרא Gemara often uses, you know, throw
the, what's that called, not the foliage, what's the top of a
tree called? The canopy or something? I don't know. Anyway, you throw
the sort of, you know, the, the, the, I'll call it... anyway,
you throw the growth after the, after the roots. Okay, so therefore
since the roots belong to ראובן, Reuven, anything that grows from the
roots also belongs to ראובן. Reuven. This idea of שדי נוף בתר
עיקר shadi nof batar ikar is often given in a different scenario.
Let's say for example, here you have ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
here you have חוץ לארץ, Chutz LaAretz, okay, and you've got a
tree that's got the roots here and the, and the head and
the top of the tree, you know, is in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and here you have an apple, okay, or whatever or an
olive, okay, is that, did that olive grow in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael or did it grow in חוץ לארץ? Chutz LaAretz? Okay, so
that's the question, do you say שדי נוף בתר עיקר, shadi nof
batar ikar, you go from this, you throw the top of the
tree, the stuff growing to where the roots are and it grew
from חוץ לארץ, Chutz LaAretz, it grew from חוץ לארץ, Chutz LaAretz,
right? Or do you say no, you know, you don't do it,
and since the apple or the olive is growing in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, it's in, you know, that's where physically in the airspace
it is, it grew in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. That's a classic
question in the גמרא Gemara in terms of how do you identify
something's location. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara has a lot of fun
with this. Let's say a guy is running to an עיר מקלט,
Ir Miklat, okay, and this is an עיר מקלט Ir Miklat and
this עיר מקלט Ir Miklat starts over here and this is outside
the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat and he jumps up into the tree.
Okay, is he in the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat yet or is
he not in the עיר מקלט Ir Miklat yet? All right, so
anyway,
so there's different ways you can ask that. Here the גמרא is
a question of ownership, right? It might be given answers based on
what הלכה halacha we're asking about. So here's the question of ownership.
Do you throw the top by the roots and since the roots
are ראובן's Reuven the top is as well or just say no,
the tops here are growing in שמעון's Shimon. airspace they belong to
שמעון. Shimon רבי מאיר סבר שדי נוף בתר עיקר, Rabbi Meir savar
shadi nof batar ikar, you throw the top of it by towards
the roots and therefore it belongs to ראובן, Reuven, רבי יהודה סבר
לאו מילתא היא שדי נוף בתר עיקר, Rabbi Yehuda savar lav milta
hi shadi nof batar ikar, you don't say that and therefore it
belongs to שמעון Shimon it's growing in שמעון's airspace that's physically where
it is. Okay, ואזדו לטעמייהו V'azdu l'ta'amayhu some have this גרסא girsa
they go according to their reasons or they say כי האי גוונא
דתניא ki hai gavna d'tanya similar to the following ברייתא braita because
it's not exactly the same debate but it's a somewhat parallel discussion,
the following ברייתא. braita. היוצא מן הגזע ומן השרשים הרי אלו של
בעל הקרקע דברי רבי מאיר. Hayotzei min hageza u'min hasharashim harei elu
shel ba'al hakarka divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי... okay so basically what you
did is, you have bought now a tree in עילאי's Ilay land.
Okay and I don't own the land, I only own the single
tree. So I don't have any rights to the land I don't
have rights to things that grow from the land but I obviously
have rights to the apples from the tree or I have rights
to if the tree grows and there are more branches I can
cut them down and use them for wood, okay, and so on,
the extra branches of the tree. Now, what happens if I've got
this tree here, okay, whatever that was, I've got this tree that's
growing in עילאי's land and I only own the tree and he
owns the land and now out from some of the roots pops
up another tree. Okay. Now in that case it's not seen as
coming from the tree it's seen as coming from the land even
though it's coming from the roots from the tree. Okay I only
own like the stuff the tree produces, the fruits, the whatever, I
don't own new trees. Only what's above. What's above... well but this
is also above ground but it came from like a root so
that's seen as coming from the ground and that's seen as not
coming from my tree. What if out of, out of the the
actual trunk another tree emerged like that again, okay, is that seen
like a fruit of the tree you know and coming from the
tree and therefore I have rights to it or is that seen
as something that came like from the ground and I don't really
have rights to it? That's the question. So let's take a look.
It really is a different question than this one תוספות Tosafot points
it out but it's somewhat parallel. Let's take a look. Okay, היוצא
מן הגזע Hayotzei min hageza if something comes from the actual trunk
ומן השרשים u'min hasharashim הרי אלו של בעל הקרקע דברי רבי מאיר.
harei elu shel ba'al hakarka divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yehuda omer no, מן הגזע של בעל האילן, min hageza shel ba'al
ha'ilan, if it comes from the trunk it belongs to the guy
who bought the tree, that's like a produce of the tree, ומן
השרשים של בעל הקרקע, u'min hasharashim shel ba'al hakarka, and from the
roots it comes from the guy who owns the land. Now this
is somewhat similar, not really, right? Because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
it all goes to the guy who owns the tree which basically
means... hold on let me just get this right one minute. One
minute. One minute. אי איהו של בעל הקרקע. Ei ihu shel ba'al
hakarka. Right, right, right, right. Right, right, right. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says, right, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says this all goes to the
guy who owns the land. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir sort of
sees things more fully in terms of where are they growing from.
Okay, and he's and now this is obviously different because in this
case the guy who owns the tree does not have air rights.
Here Shimon has air rights, right? So because Shimon has air rights,
there's a reason to say that the stuff that's growing in the
air is Shimon's. Here the guy who owns the tree does not
have air rights, so it's not really a direct parallel. Okay, and
תוספות Tosafot makes that point. But nevertheless, it's a somewhat similar because
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is sort of saying, I'm going to default
to give everything to the guy who owns the land. It all
grows from the land, so I'm going to give it to the
guy who owns the land. Whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, no,
this is growing above ground, and you have rights to stuff that
grow from the tree, I'm going to consider this growing from the
tree. So it's somewhat similar that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is oriented
towards the fact that it's growing from the land and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is sort of oriented more towards the fact that it's
above ground. All right, so but it's not an exact parallel. ותנן
נמי גבי ערלה כי האי גוונא, V'tman nami gabi orlah ki hai
gavna, we have a similar משנה mishna by ערלה. orlah. אילן היוצא
מן הגזע ומן השרשים חייב בערלה. Ilan hayotzei min hageza umin hashorashim
chayav ba'orlah.
Let's say I own this whole thing, and now I have a
new tree coming out. Is it considered this tree is like five
years old, is this considered like a part of this tree and
therefore not חייב in ערלה, orlah, is this considered a new tree?
Okay, so the משנה says that either way, it's if it's a
new tree and it's חייב in ערלה. orlah. So it's like you
look at it as coming from the ground essentially, דברי רבי מאיר.
divrei Rabbi Meir. That's again sort of רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir paralleling.
You look at it coming from the ground, he's paralleling
himself by the other question of ownership. רבי יהודה אומר מן הגזע
פטור ומן השרשים חייב. Rabbi Yehuda omer min hageza patur umin hashorashim
chayav. No, from the trunk it's like a fruit, it's not ערלה,
orlah, it's in like a new branch, and from the root it
is a new tree. וצריכין, V'tzrichin, you need to tell me both
cases. ערלה orlah and the case of this split ownership. דאי אשמעינן
קמייתא, Di ashmian kamayti, if it were the case that one guy
owns the tree and one guy owns the land, הכא אמר רבי
יהודה, hacha amar Rabbi Yehuda, משום דממונא, mishum d'mamona,
that's where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that I'm willing to say
that it's considered to the owner of the tree because it's just
a monetary issue. So I'll favor the owner of the tree and
say that it's like a new branch. אבל גבי ערלה דאיסורא, Aval
gabi orlah d'issura, but by ערלה orlah where we're dealing with an
איסור, issur, maybe I should be strict and treat it like at
least a ספק ערלה safek orlah and you know be חייב in
ערלה. orlah. Okay, אימא מודי ליה לרבי מאיר, eima modei lei l'Rabbi
Meir, maybe he should agree
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that he's going to treat it like
ערלה. orlah. ואי אתמר בהא, V'im itmar beha, and if you just
said the case of ערלה, orlah, maybe that's where רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is strict, אבל בהיא אימא מודי ליה לרבי יהודה, aval behi
eima modei lei l'Rabbi Yehuda, but in the case of monetary ownership
maybe there he will award it to the guy who owns the
tree, צריכי, tzrichi, you need both cases. So those are similar, there's
a question of whether you view it as a new tree or
as an or as a new branch. Okay, but nevertheless, it's not
exactly the same as our case. Our case really is a difference
where one guy owns the airspace and one guy owns the ground
and it's physically you want the stuff that's in the airspace, but
it's growing from somebody else's ground. Okay, let's look at the last
piece. אמר רבי שמעון כל שאינו יכול לפשוט, Amar Rabbi Shimon kol
she'eyno yachol lifshot, so רבי שמעון goes by the ability to physically
access it. So the גמרא says, אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, amri d'bei
Rabbi Yannai, ובבלבד שלא יאנס. ubvilvad shelo ye'anes. It can,
it's only if he's not risking, like he can't say, well, if
I can dangle by my toes and you know then I could
reach it. No, no, no. Means being able to reach it reasonably
without risking yourself, you know, without without like you know
risking your safety. Okay, so that's the determinant factor. Okay, now, does
it mean without any artificial assistance? Right, let's say I can say
I could lower myself down by a presumably by a rope, presumably
that doesn't help, presumably it means just by yourself you can access
it. בעי רבי ינאי ואיתימא רבי ירמיה מגיע לנופו ואינו מגיע לעיקרו
מגיע לעיקרו ואינו מגיע לנופו מה? Ba'ei Rabbi Yannai v'it'eima Rabbi Yirmiya
magiya l'nofo v'eino magiya l'ikaro magiya l'ikaro v'eino magiya l'nofo mah? תיקו.
Teiku. Right, so this is the obvious question to ask, which is,
okay, what does it mean I should reach it? Let's say the
roots start over here, and but the actual the thing I want
is over there. Well, if I reach down I can sort of
get get access to the roots but I can't get access to
the actual tomato that I want. Or it's the reverse, right,
that it's sort of the
tomato is over here, but the roots are are down here and
I can reach down and access the tomato but I can't access
the roots. So what determines access? Okay, so the גמרא says, תיקו,
Teiku, presumably רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmiya.
What? Okay, fine, but in the name of רבי... okay, good point.
תיקו. Teiku. Okay, good point. אמר אפרים ספרא תלמידו דריש לקיש משמיה
דריש לקיש, Amar Efrayim Safra talmido d'Reish Lakish mishmei d'Reish Lakish, said
Efrayim scribes the student of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish in the name
of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, הלכה כרבי שמעון, halacha k'Rabbi Shimon, we
rule like רבי שמעון. It's about physical access. Which is funny, because
that seems, if you ask me, that seems to be the one
that was like, I don't know, somehow too a little too pragmatic,
maybe people like pragmatism, you know, but it's not as much conceptual.
There's a core conceptual issue here, you know, is it about ground
rights or air rights? But anyway he says, no, since there's no
clear way to determine that, we go by access. ואמרו קמיה דשבור
מלכא, Va'amru k'mei d'Shavor Malka, they said this to the שבור מלכא.
Shavor Malka. Now who's שבור מלכא... Shavor Malka... שבור מלכא *Shvor Malka*,
so if you look at רש"י *Rashi*, anyway, let's finish it and
then I'll tell you what it is. אמר להו *Amar lehu*, and
he said to them that we rule like רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*,
and the שבור מלכא *Shvor Malka* said back, אפריון נמטיה לרבי שמעון
*Aperion namtei le'Rebbi Shimon*, like glory should be given to רבי שמעון
*Rebbi Shimon*. So there's two interesting questions here: who is שבור מלכא
*Shvor Malka* and what's an אפריון *aperion*? So if you look at
רש"י *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* says קמיה דשבור מלכא *kamei de'Shvor Malka*, רש"י
*Rashi* says לי נראה שבור מלכא ממש *Li nireh Shvor Malka mamash*,
he was really a king, ומלך פרס היה *u'melech Paras haya*, and
he was the king of Persia, ובקי בדינים *u'baki b'dinim*, and he
was friends with שמואל *Shmuel*. Okay, the גמרא *Gemara* discusses discussions between
him and שמואל *Shmuel*. So it's funny that like they're telling him
a הלכה *halachic* פסק *psak*, but רש"י *Rashi* says, you know, he
was interested in law and he took interest in these legal disputes
of other cultures. ואמרו ליה הא דרבי שמעון דמתניתין קמיה וקלסה *v'amru
lei ha d'Rebbi Shimon d'matnisin kameih v'kalsah*, and they told him, oh,
you know, there's an interesting debate in הלכה *halacha* about this issue
and here's רבי שמעון's *Rebbi Shimon's* position. He said, oh, that makes
a lot of sense. Okay, so it wasn't a הלכה *halachic* פסק
*psak*, he was just sharing this with
some stranger, I mean, whatever, some non-Jew, you know, about Jewish law.
So אמר אפריון נמטיה לרבי שמעון *amar Aperion namtei le'Rebbi Shimon*. אפריון
*Aperion*, now what is אפריון *aperion*? יקבל חן מאיתנו *Yikabel chen me'itanu*.
So רש"י *Rashi* reads the word אפריון *aperion*, the יון *yon* means
as possessive, our, our favor should be given to רבי שמעון *Rebbi
Shimon*. על דבר זה *al davar zeh*. Okay, so ואיכא דאמרי שבור
מלכא שמואל דבכמה דוכתי קרי ליה הכי *v'ika d'amri Shvor Malka Shmuel
d'be'chama douchti kari lei hachi*, that they that שמואל *Shmuel*, because שמואל
*Shmuel* was close to the real שבור מלכא *Shvor Malka*, this Persian
king, sometimes they called him שבור מלכא *Shvor Malka*. But רש"י *Rashi*
says ותמיהא לי *u'tmiha li*, what does it mean ואמרו ליה *v'amru
lei*, what does it mean they said to שמואל *Shmuel*? Hey, there's
this position of רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* in the משנה *Mishna*. What,
שמואל *Shmuel* didn't know the position of רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*? הא
דרבי שמעון דמתניתין אטו שמואל לא הוה ידע להא דמתניתין *Ha d'Rebbi
Shimon d'matnisin
atu Shmuel lo hava yada le'ha d'matnisin*?
What? הלכה *Halacha*? Ah, so אי הא דאפרים ספרא *ei ha d'Efraim
Safra*, maybe what they told שמואל *Shmuel* was, oh, אפרים *Efraim* the
ספרא *Safra* in the name of ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* פסק *paskens*
this way. אטו אילו לא אמר ריש לקיש הלכה כרבי שמעון שמואל
מי לא קים בדיניה דמקלסה לרבי שמעון *Atu ilu lo amar Reish
Lakish halacha k'Rebbi Shimon Shmuel mi lo kayim b'dineia d'mikalsa le'Rebbi Shimon*?
If שמואל *Shmuel* liked רבי שמעון's *Rebbi Shimon's* position, שמואל *Shmuel* could
have praised רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* on his own. He didn't need
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* to פסק *pasken* like רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*
for him to then praise רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*. He didn't say
give, you know, he didn't praise ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, he praised
רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*. עד דשמע משמיה דריש לקיש דהלכתא כוותיה *ad
d'shama mishmei d'Reish Lakish d'hilchata k'vateih*. So there's one question whether שבור
מלכא *Shvor Malka* is some non-Jewish Persian king who likes the Jewish
law, or whether it's שמואל *Shmuel*. And רש"י *Rashi* sides by the
first. And the other question is what אפריון *aperion* means. So רש"י
*Rashi* says it means the יון *yon* means our, means our favor,
but if you look at the side there's an interesting אפריון *aperion*,
right. So if you look at the side, it says גירסת הערוך
הוו ליה אפריא לרבי שמעון *Girsat he'Aruch hava lei apria le'Rebbi Shimon*,
what? אפריא *Apria* is
like a bed,
like a bier to carry somebody on. Right, but then, right, but
the language
אפריא
*apria* is a bed, so in Aramaic.
So אפריון עשה לו המלך
שלמה *Aperion asa lo ha'melech Shlomo*, really?
Interesting. Okay. Alright. So anyway, look at the side, you have the
ערוך *Aruch*, he says גירסת הערוך הוו ליה אפריא לרבי שמעון ופירוש
חזק בלשון פרסי ישר כוחו ישר חילו *Girsat he'Aruch hava lei apria
le'Rebbi Shimon upirush chozek bilshon Parsi yashar kocho yashar cheilo*. So the
idea ישר כוחך *Yashar kochacha*, ישר כוחך *Yashar kochacha* to רבי שמעון
*Rebbi Shimon*, right? He
should give strength to רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon*. So okay, so that's
one word. And the and it's not the יון *yon*, it's אפריא
*apria*.
And then ספרים אחרים אפריא לרבי שמעון ברכה ומלשון בן פורת יוסף
*Sfarim acherim apria le'Rebbi Shimon bracha umilshon Ben Porat Yosef*, fruitfulness, כלומר
יפרו וירבו חכמים ונבונים כמותו *klomar yifru v'yirbu chachamim u'nevonim k'moto*. So
many different possible explanations what this... but אפריון עשה לו המלך שלמה
*Aperion asa lo ha'melech Shlomo*, right? So it is interesting that people
are not sort of referencing that. But I also think it's interesting
to read: what does it mean that the last words of the
whole מסכת בבא מציעא Bava Metzia. *Masechet Bava Metzia*, right, are from
the words of a שבור מלכא *Shvor Malka*? Is it sort of
like saying, like, you know, is it some sense, you know, this
is ultimately, you know, דיני ממונות *Dinei Mamonot* are things that secular
law deals with all the time, you know? And on the one
hand, there are things like this, which you could say, well, what
makes this religious law? I mean, things like about לא תלין פעולת
שכיר *Lo talin pe'ulat sachir*, רבית *Ribbit*, I mean, those clearly are
מצוות *Mitzvot* about. But we're about to go into בבא בתרא *Bava
Batra*, which is all like there's almost no פסוק *pasuk* in the
תורה *Torah* that בבא בתרא *Bava Batra* refers to. It's almost, you
know, some people say that's the great thing about it, it's like
all a rabbinic, you know, construction, not a תקנה *takana*, but the
rabbis developing laws to govern interpersonal relationships, right? So, you know, does
that make it... how do we feel about that in terms of
that as תורה *Torah*, as like the religious component of it, when
it's less an elaboration, you know, of פסוקים *psukim* in the תורה
*Torah*, of מצוות *Mitzvot*? It's more just laws that find parallels in
secular society and so on. So I think it's interesting to reflect
on that, that the sort of summary of בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia*
could be these words from this like, you know, non-Jewish king about
oh, that was a brilliant idea. Okay, right?
So how much is this... are we looking for, you know, for
validation? Are we looking, you know, I mean the תורה *Torah* sometimes
says that, right? The תורה *Torah* says, what? What does the תורה
*Torah* say? You know, וראו כל עמי הארץ כי שם ה' נקרא
עליך *V'rau kol am ha'aretz ki shem Hashem nikra alecha*... רק עם
*Rak am*... חכם ונבון הגוי הגדול הזה כי מי גוי גדול אשר
לו חוקים ומשפטים צדיקים. ki mi goy gadol asher lo chukim umishpatim
tzadikim. Right, it says, you know, that somehow these are just laws
which even from a non-Jewish and not religious perspective will be seen
as just, right? So again, it's very interesting having this voice to
end up בבא מציעא. Okay? הדרן עלך הבית והעליה וסליקא לך מסכת
בבא מציעא. Hadran alach HaBayit VeHaAliya usalika lach maseches Bava Metzia. We
will continue בבא בתרא.